A Guide to the Photographs, Series 1011-1081 FA438
Rockefeller Archive Center
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA), 1946-1968, n.d.; 1027; 6.2 Cubic Feet 19 boxes.
  - Venezuela, 4
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Carpentry, Prints: 8 (Box 11, Folder 212)
      42. Simple cabinets where food and eating utensils can be kept screened against the numerous posts which infest the simple rural dwellings of Venezuela are constructed from scrap lumber by housewives who attend the carpentry classes offered by CBR. This class, similar to those offered in CBR home demonstration centers throughout Venezuela, is meeting at the Home Demonstration Training Center in San Felipe. 43. Here is an almost completed window, constructed by members of the class in simple carpentry offered by CBR and Hogar Campesino home demonstration agents in the vicinity of La Trilla-Marincito. Tools were donated by members of the class, for the most part, and the thatched roof shop formerly was a shelter for drying tobacco and donated by one of the more affluent citizens of the community. 44. CBR and local education authorities in El Roble, state of Carabobo, have combined forces to expand the activities of the cillage school so that it also serves as a neighborhood center and provides facilities for adult education. Older children constructed these hobby horses for their younger brothers and sisters at a carpentry class. Activities also include serving a mid-morning lunch to school children from CBR kitchen, a community garden and classes in cooking, sewing, and rudimentary carpentry. 45. Women attending the class in carpentry at the CBR home demonstration training center in San Felipe learn to construct rudimentary furniture. 46. These teen-aged girls are receiving from CBR's Sra. Yolanda Belisario de Melendez in rudimentary carpentry at the center in Marin, State of Yaracuy. 47. Furniture is constructed from scrap lumber for the new CBR neighborhood center of Albarico in Yaracuy. When completed this piece, which the girl is aligning, will be a couch and end table combined. 48. No caption. 49. CBR and Hogar Camesino home demonstration workers instruct villagers of the La Trilla-Marincito community in simple carpentry. The present project is the construction of window frames as part of a project to ventilate the airless mud and cane houses in which most of the people live.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Community Center, Prints: 12 (Box 11, Folder 213)
      50. This is the main street, almost the only street, of Albarico, Yaracuy, where CBR established its most recent community center. 51. This charming little community is Albarico, Yaracuy, a group of pastel cottages shaded by coconut palms, where CBR founded it's most recent neighborhood center. 52. Mothers and children gather outside the neighborhood center "Turin" in the Yaracuy village of Marin. 53. Professional personnel attending the CBR Home Demonstration Training seminar last summer learned to construct building blocks such as this one shown in the photo which they, in turn, are prepared to teach others to construct and thereby disseminate how-to-do-it detail regarding this durable, but cheap and readily accessible, building material. 54. In the yard behind the neighborhood center "Tiuna" in the Yaracuy settlement of Marin, villagers frequently gather for volley ball. 55. CBR collaborated once again with a community project when Home Demonstration training director Elba Velez supervised the remodeling and equipping of a San Felipe nursery for the children of working mothers. She is shown here (facing camera) in front of the building, discussing the project with the director, Mrs. Claudia de Sainz. 56. CBR's Home Demonstration Training Director Elba Velez discusses the program for the new San Felipe children's nursery with Mrs. Claudia de Sainz in the latters office. The portrait of the South American liberator, Simon Bolivar, hanging over Mrs. De Sainz's desk, was among the many gifts received from the government. 57. The San Felipe nursery "Jardin de Infancia Simon Rodriguez" (named for the tutor Simon Bolivar) is among the most beautifully equipped in Latin America. A project of the Damas Bolivarianas, a women's civic group named for the Venezuelan liberator Simon Bolivar, the actual planning was done by CBR home demonstration training director Elbe Velez. 58. The director of the San Felipe children's nursery, Mrs. Claudia de Sainz, arranges some of the excellent equipment supplied for the completely modern kitchen, contributed in large part by the Venezuelan government. 59. Members of the little mountain community of Albarico in Yaracuy, with CBR's Elba Velez advising, plan the repair of a fine, old colonial house which has fallen into ruin and was contributed by a member of the community for use as a neighborhood center. 60. CBR's Elba Velez, director of the Home Demonstration program for Yaracuy shows a group of CBR and Hogar Campesino "demostradoras" how to operate an opaque machine, one of several visual aids employed in civic health and improvement campaigns. The instruction was part of a training course conducted by Miss Velez recently in the CBR model Center at San Felipe, Yaracuy. 61. Visual aids study includes the operation of an opaque machine. CBR and Hogar Campesino Home Demonstration agents watch while Director Elba Velez projects a picture.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Crafts, Prints: 4 (Box 11, Folder 214)
      62. A fashion show concluded the third short course offered at the CBR Home Demonstration Training seminar for professional personnel, conducted last summer at the San Felipe training center. This course, one of several offered, was devoted to clothing and personal appearance. 63. Women of the Yaracuy village of Marin gather at the neighborhood center where, under the direction of a CBR home demonstration worker, they learn to sew. 64. Women and girls of the La Trilla-Marincito community gather in the home of an owner of one of the few sewing machines in the settlement for a sewing class conducted by members of the CBR and Hogar Campesino home demonstration training course team. 65. Women at the neighborhood center "Tiuna" in the Yaracay village of Marin prepare material for the soles of the "alpargatos" on the table. Alpargatos are a type of sandal worn universally by the poor in Venezuela. 66. Housewives learn to make shirts from feed sacks during the Home Demonstration training course visit to La Trilla-Marincito for a sewing class. 67. No caption. 68. A CBR home demonstration worker advises while a member of the sewing class of La Trilla-Marincito cuts part of a shirt. This garment is made from a feed sack. 69. No caption.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Education, Prints: 3 (Box 11, Folder 215)
      70. Farm youth of Marin watch intently as CBR technician Juan B. Acosta points out the characteristics of good corn seed. 71. The La Trilla Marincito Civic Committee told Governor Hector Blanco Fombona of Yaracuy that La Trilla needs a new school house to replace this old one. 72. CBR technician Juan B. Acosta aided by Evilio Tovar explains to farm children of the Marin community in Yaracuy which type of ear should be selected for seed corn. The demonstration was made at the neighborhood center. The best ears grow low on the stalk.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Gardening, Prints: 6 (Box 12, Folder 216)
      73. School children of La Trilla-Marincito, guided by CBR Hogar Comesino Home Demonstration agents, prepare a model garden. 74. Preparation of a seed bed is part of the task of gardening undertaken by school children of the La Trilla-Marincito community. CBR's Corina Garcia assists and instructs the youngsters in their task. 75. CBR Technician Juan B. Acosta gives an enthusiastic group of young farmers would-be farmers pointers for identifying good seed in a demonstration at the neighborhood center in Marin in the state of Yaracuy. 76. Hogar Campesino Home Demonstration agents work in the Center's demonstration garden. Vegetables are used in the cooking classes taught at the Center. 77. People in Marin in Yaracuy combine tools and time working in the community garden, grown on a plot behind the CBR neighborhood center, which is directed by home demonstration agent Sra. Yolanda Belisario de Melendez. Her husband, a CBR agricultural agent known as a "perito," advises the novice gardeners on the care of their crops. 78. School children of La Trilla-Marincito community center prepare the soil for a school yard garden. Little girls in the background are preparing a seed bed. CBR and Hogar Campesino home demonstration workers chose this settlement as a project for their recent training course in Yaracuy.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, General, Prints: 7 (Box 12, Folder 217)
      79. CBR supervised credit agent Evelio Tovar discusses a credit plan with Eliseo Geraterol and family of La Trilla, Yaracuy. 80. Sr. Eliseo Geraterol, vice president of the la Trilla delegation elected to call upon Governor Hector Fombona of yaracuy, discusses the problems of the little backwoods community with CBR home demonstration supervisor of the zone, Elba Velez. 81. CBR Elba Velez reviews the program of the joint conference held with Hogar Campesino to develop home demonstration techniques to aid rural Velezuelan families. Graciela Gutierrez, HC supervisor for the four-state area of Carabobo, Cojedes, Lara, and Yaracuy, sits to the right of Miss Velez. 82. Typical home in La Trilla, project community for CBR and Hogar Campesino Home Demonstration agents. 83. Street scene in La Trilla Marincito where CBR Hogar Campesino home demonstration workers began a test program of community betterment. 84. Applicants Eliseo Geraterol discusses his prospects for supervised credit with CBR agent Evelio Tovar. 85. Farm and Home planning for the whole family. A potential applicant and his family in Yaracuy listen carefully as the plan is explained by the CBR technician.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Home Improvement, Prints: 7 (Box 12, Folder 218)
      86. Sr. Carlos Manuel Orvieto and his Senora of the La Trilla-Marincito community were so impressed with the improvement program initiated by members of CBR and Hogar Campesino workers in the La Trilla-Marincito community that, after "opening" a new window in their old house of mud and cane, they decided to build a new house, this one of cement. Sr. Orvieto applied the rules of carpentry he learned in the CBR-Hogar Campesino class to construct this double window in his home. 87. The man of the house lends a hand in fitting the frame of a new window in his cane and mud house in the Yaracuy community of La Trilla. A representative of Hogar Campesino, the farm home workers of the Venezuelan Ministry of Agriculture offer a bit if advice. 88. CBR-Hogar Campesino Home demonstration team shows a La Trilla housewife how to construct a window. 89. The new window works fine. CBR Home demonstration supervisor for Yaracuy, Elbe Velez, explains the principle of hinges to a group of citizens of the La Trilla-Marincito community where several windows are "opened" as part of the CBR-Hogar Campesino training course for home demonstration workers, who instructed the people of the community in the construction of window frames and shutters. 90. Use of "tierra-cemento" blocks in rural construction is shown here in the addition to a Yaracuy farm house. This was a part of a demonstration for the CBR Home Demonstration Training Seminar for professional personnel, held at San Felipe last summer. 91. Construction from blocks of "tierra-cemento", a cheap convenient material for use in low-cost housing comprised part of the subject matter for the fifth course, which dealt with living quarters, of the Home Demonstration Training seminar for professional personnel held last summer in San Felipe. 92. CBR and Hogar Campesino home demonstration workers have taught the people of La Trilla Marincito (Yaracuy State) to construct window frames. The "duena de la casa" is adding the final touches to the window she has "opened" to ventilate her one-room mud and cane house.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Hygiene, Prints: 4 (Box 12, Folder 219)
      93. Toweling down after a shower at the children's day nursery in San Felipe, this boy is ready to don a clean uniform and begin the day's round of activities, which include study, mid-morning "meriends," play, lunch, rest and group singing. 94. Habits of hygiene are taught the youngsters at the model San Felipe nursery for the children of working mothers. Many of them never had contact with comb or toothbrush before. Each little lavatory is built to size for the youngsters, most of them of pre-school age. 95. Tiny shower stalls, built to size, accommodate the children attending the San Felipe nursery, designed by CBR home demonstration training director, Elba Velez, and promoted by the Damas Bolivarianas whose honorary president is the wife of the governor of Yaracuy. 96. This child readily peels off his "home clothes" and hangs them in the handy little wardrobe at the children's nursery in San Felipe. After a shower, he will slip into a clean uniform provided by the nursery.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Nutrition, Prints: 14 (Box 12, Folder 220)
      97. No caption. 98. Leaders of the Yaracuy capital of San Felipe joined with volunteer mothers in serving the children at the milk station on the day the CBR Model Center was inaugurated. 99. CBR home economist Elba Velez measures one of the daily attendants of the feeding station at the Center. This is part of a routine health check, which includes periodic examination by a physician. 100. Children attending the daily feeding station at the Center have gained an average of two pounds during three months. Director Elba Velez checks their weight each week. 101. CBR Supervisor Corina offers a few gentle hints, as her little helper - an attendant at the milk station of the Model Center in San Felipe - feeds a rabbit carrots from the demonstration garden. Rabbits and chickens are kept penned next to the garden and like it, they demonstrate to persons of the community the sort of individual activity they can adapt to small space and thereby supplement their often inadequate diets. 102. Volunteer mothers serve breakfast each week day at the milk station of the CBR Model Center in San Felipe, capital of the State of Yaracuy. 103. Youngsters attending the nursery for children or working mothers in San Felipe wait for their "merienda". For many of them this nutritious mid-morning meal of milk and cereal, perhaps, with fruit, is the most wholesome diet they have had. The children also receive a nutritious lunch. 104. Volunteer mother serves milk and cereal to children at the milk station of the neighborhood center "Tiuma" established by CBR Home Demonstration workers in the Yaracuy village of Marin. 105. Hungry children peer over a bottle of cod liver oil, waiting for their daily breakfast at the CBR Model Center milk station in San Felipe, State of Yaracuy. Mothers of some of these youngsters prepare the food, serve it and wash the dishes. 106. This young "musiu" (foreigner) is being a brave girl and taking her cod liver oil at the milk station of the CBR Home Demonstration neighborhood center in Marin. 107. Certain school age children also receive "breakfasts" at the milk station of the neighborhood center "Tiuna" in the Yaracuy village of Marin. 108. Children from the poorest home of San Felipe gather each week day morning for servings of fruit, cereal, milk, plus a does of cod liver oil, at the CBR Model Center in San Felipe. 109. Pre-school age children of the Yaracuy village of Marin receive cod liver oil, milk, and cereal, served each morning by volunteer mothers at the neighborhood center "Tiuna", operated under the supervision of CBR home demonstration workers. 110. Hungry children of the Yaracuy village of Marin make short work of cereal and milk at the CBR Home Demonstration Milk Station.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Sanitation, Prints: 6 (Box 12, Folder 221)
      111. Young CBR home demonstration trainees learn poster-making techniques that will help teach fellow Venezuelans the principles of home management and sanitation. 112. Each youngster at the Don Simon Rodriguez nursery, in San Felipe, has his own sheet on its own shelf and sets up his own little cot for the daily rest period. Some of these children have not slept on individual beds before and few of them were acquainted with the luxury of clean sheets. 113. This little girl carefully spreads the sheet on her small cot, ready to take her daily nap at the Simon Rodriguez nursery in San Felipe, state of Yaracuy. Funds to equip the nursery were raised by the Damas Bolivarianas whose president is the first lady of the state, Dona Esther Valery de Cordida. 114. CBR and Hogar Campesino home economy agents join in a poster contest, demonstrating this medium of visual aid in a community health or improvement campaign. The contest took place during a recent training course for home demonstration workers, conducted by CBR's Elba Velez, director for this work in Tachira. 115. A pretty CBR "demostradora" shows her entry in the poster contest, conducted during the recent home demonstration training course in Yaracuy. Her poster says "Always keep your home painted and clean. Cooperate in the Clean-Up Campaign". 116. Prize winning poster says to destroy flies, which carry germs. Poster contest was part of a visual aids study undertaken by CBR and Hogar Campesino home demonstration workers.
    - CBR, Yaracuy, Training Farm, Prints: 33 (Box 12, Folder 222)
      117. - 147. No caption. 148. Yaracuy - San Pablo. Damage done by army worm. 149. Yaracuy - San Felipe. Identification of army worm on corn.
    - CBR, Miscellaneous, Carpentry, Prints: 2 (Box 12, Folder 223)
      1. Students at home demonstration agents school learning how to make simple furniture so they can teach Venezuelan rural housewives to do the same. 2. In the woodcrafts class the students learn to fashion simple utilitarian objects for home and school from scrap lumber. Note the box with handle is identical to that wherein the bottle caps and shells for arithmetic study are kept.
    - CBR, Miscellaneous, Education, Prints: 5 (Box 12, Folder 224)
      3. These two engrossed little girls are learning to count on an abacus of shells. 4. The reading lesson concerns Venezuela's flag, "la bandera." An older student points, and the younger ones recite that the flag is pretty, is red, yellow and blue and has seven stars. On the table is a drawing of the "aparato digestivo," the digestive system. 5. The chapel dating from colonial times at Monte Sacro farm in the Chirgua Valley has been restored to serve as a school for the children of the farm's employees. 6. Reconstructed, but its fine, old lines unchanged, the former Monte Sacro Chapel reflects its change in status by a simple sign. 7. No caption.
    - CBR, Miscellaneous, Gardening, Prints: 1 (Box 12, Folder 225)
      8. Vegetable beds are neatly bordered by cement blocks, and the children are expected to weed and cultivate them. Together with their gardening instruction, the youngsters receive important guidance in nutrition.
    - CBR, Miscellaneous, General, Prints: 51 (Box 12, Folder 226)
      9. Nothing to be afraid of: This seems to be the philosophy of seven year old Victor Raul Bolivar who helps his father, Juan, a PAAP bee expert. However, little Victor is wearing a protective veil in case the bees do not agree. 10. No caption. 11. No caption. 12. No caption. 13. No caption. 14. Youth Club Project: Venezuelan Youth Club (5-V) member showing one of his budded (improved) orange trees produced with guidance of MAC (Ministry of Agriculture) - CBR technician. 15. A rural Venezuelan audience watches CBR motion picture on good health practices. 16. Mrs. Millie Prosdocimi, director of the CBR Home Demonstration Section, delivers a diploma to Miss Flamina Oberti, director of the Red Cross Social Service, at the conclusion of the series of courses offered by CBR in Caracas to social workers of the government and various official and private social agencies. Next to Mrs. Prosdocimi is her assistant, Miss Elda Marquina. 17. A scene at the party which closed the series of courses offered by the CBR home demonstration section, headed by Mrs. Millie Prosdocimi, to Venezuelan social workers. On the table can be seen some of the objects prepared in Course No. VIII: Rural Development. 18. No caption. 19. No caption. 20. No caption. 21. No caption. 22. No caption. 23. No caption. 24. No caption. 25. Los credos son sometidos a pesaje para constatar los aumentos de peso. 26. No caption. 27. Learning how to iron. 28. Six grade girls sewing. 29. They also learn to wash clothes. 30. Farmers signing their agreement with BAP. CBR-Quarterly report, Oct-Dec 1961. 31. A campesino from San Nicolas de Bari looks over his harness. They form part of the equipment given by the BAP on credit. 32. Noriche palm typical of the Guyana zone which are used primarily for fibers. 33. Prepared for work, Domingo Peralta and his burro. Domingo had received the training in the animal drawn implement of the CBR program. 34. Part of the CBR's exhibit at the Campesino Fair, Maracay. 35. The Pro 5-V Club Association and the publications programs at the Campesino Fair. 36. 300 Kaki Campbel Ducks were imported from Holland during January. Here is one of the three duck houses and corrals constructed for that purpose. 37. Home gardening. 38. Irrigation. 39. Laying hens. 40. Fruit growing. 41. The carpenters. 42. The auto mechanics. 43. Toward the end of the semester, some practice teaching classes were started and those are continuing more intensively during the rest of the course. Here, one of the teacher trainees puts on a demonstration on measurement in the machine shop. 44. Another demonstrates the use of the shaper. 45. Los conejos son una explotacion comun dentro de los proyectos 5-V de Azaguas, 1967. 46. El trabajo preliminer del Dr. Canuto Cardona, como experto en le guminosas comestibles, mas la publicacion que se esta hacienda sobre el cultivo de carotas, constituyen un valioso aporte a los planes de los organismos patrocinantes hacia el fomento del cultivo de la carota. 1966. 47. A roadside salesman of pineapple near Valera in the Andes. (CBR quarterly report, Jan-Mar 1961.) 48. No caption. 49. No caption. 50. Right Here! Dr. Tiburcio Linares of PAAP shows Jesus Maria Cabrera where an injection should be made on a Brown Swiss cow. 51. No caption. 52. No caption. 53. No caption. 54. No caption. 55. A hydrologist points to a place for perforating a well in Lara. 56. The sugar cane industry is highly developed in Lara. 57. The Supply and Demand Study was completed during the quarter. 58. Prospect of the future fish market for Maracaibo (Maracaibo Wholesale Market Study). 59. Another view of the Maracaibo market.
    - CBR, Miscellaneous, Hygiene, Prints: 1 (Box 12, Folder 227)
      60. Learning good health is part of the procedure at the Center's feeding station. Children are taught to wash their hands and teeth and comb their hair.
    - CBR, Miscellaneous, No Caption, Prints: 86 (Box 12, Folder 228)
      61. - 146. No caption.
    - CBR, Miscellaneous, Nutrition, Prints: 2 (Box 12, Folder 229)
      147. Assistance of mothers allows stations to handle 50 to 60 children at play. 148. CBR staff member shows trainees how to make use of visual aids in home demonstration work.
    - CBR, Miscellaneous, Rural Youth Club, Prints: 28 (Box 12, Folder 230)